Guide to the Associate Board of the Women's Christian College (Madras, India) Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Associate Board of the Women's Christian College (Madras, India) Records
1942-1973
RG 187
Yale University Divinity School Library
2
(4 boxes)
The Associate Board of the Women's Christian College, Madras, was the American governing body of the College, which was founded in 1915 in Madras, India, as a joint venture of several British and American mission boards.
Women's Christian College (Madras, India). Associate Board
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the New York office of the United Church Board for World Ministries
Biographical / Historical
The Women's Christian College, Madras was opened in July 1915 with forty-one students. Affiliated with the University of Madras, it was among the first institutions for higher education for women in South India and was under the management of a Council representing the following missionary bodies: Church Missionary Society, Church of England Zenana Missionary Society, London Missionary Society, Wesleyan Methodist Missionary Society, Church of Scotland Mission, United Free Church of Scotland Mission, Arcot Assembly, American Baptist Telugu Mission, American Madura Mission, Methodist Episcopal Misison, Canadian Presbyterian Mission, American Evangelical Lutheran Mission. Miss Eleanor McDougall, formerly Classical Lecturer at Westfield College was principal for the first twenty years.
The Associate Board of the Women's Christian College, Madras was formerly known as the American Section of the Governing Board. In 1954 the Associate Board had representatives from the following boards and societies: American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, Woman's American Baptist Foreign Missionary Society, Woman's Auxiliary to the National Council of the Protestant Episcopal Church, The Women's Missionary Society of the United Lutheran Church in America, Woman's Division of Christian Service of the Board of Missions and Church Extension of The Methodist Church, Department of Women's Work of the Mission Boards Reformed Church in America, The Woman's Missionary Society of the United Church of Canada, and Mount Holyoke-in-Madras.
Christa Seva Vidhyalaya was founded in 1945 as a Missionary Training Centre in the Women's Christian College, Madras. Its purpose was to provide training for Indian women graduates who were seeking to pursue leadership posistions in Christian educational, evangelistic, and medical service.
Scope and Contents
I. Associate Board of the WCCM
II. Women's Christian College, Madras
III. Christa Seva Vidhyalaya
There are minutes and meeting records for each of these related organizations. These would appear to be the official archives of the Associate Board because the material includes original financial records and the official seal of the Board. The minutes, reports, publications, and correspondence related to the Women's Christian College, Madras itself, and the Christa Seva Vidhyalaya were most likely sent to the Associate Board as documentation of their activities.
Arrangement
I. Associate Board of the WCCM
II. Women's Christian College, Madras
III. Christa Seva Vidhyalaya
Universities and colleges -- India; Women's colleges -- India; Women's Christian College (Madras, India)
- Associate Board of the WCCM, Series I
  - Minutes and meeting records
    - Minutes of the American Section of the Governing Board, Women's Christian College, Madras, Inc., 1943 May - 1947 Sep (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Minutes of the American Section of the Governing Board, Women's Christian College, Madras, Inc.; name changed to Associate Board of the WCCM in 1950, 1948 Feb - 1950 Dec (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Minutes of the Associate Board, 1951 May - 1963 Oct (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
    - Announcements of meetings, 1948 May - 1963 Oct (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Annual meeting agendas, 1948 May - 1963 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Lists of Board members, 1943-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Other Board records
    - Financial records (Box 1, Folder 9a)
    - Seal of the Associate Board (Box 2)
- Women's Christian College, Madras, Series II
  - Minutes
    - College Council minutes, 1943 Mar, 1972 Sep (Box 3, Folder 10-15)
  - Reports
    - College Council reports, 1942-1971 (Box 3, Folder 16-20)
  - Publications
    - Brochures (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - The Sunflower (student magazine) (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Histories, handbook (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Christa Seva Vidhyalaya, Series III
  - Minutes
    - Board of Management minutes, 1948 Mar, 1973 Sep (Box 4, Folder 24-30)
    - British Committee, Corresponding Board minutes, 1949 Dec, 1958 Jun (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence
    - To/from Margaret Wigan and Hester Huggins, 1948 May, 1955 May (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - To/from Elizabeth Paul and Pauline Cutler, 1968 Nov, 1973 Jul (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Circular letters - Elizabeth Paul, 1969 Mar, 1973 Dec (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Circular letters - staff, 1956-1970 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - To/from Benjamin Johnson and Hester Huggins, 1948 Jun, Nov (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Letters acknowledging receipts, 1948-1949 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Publications
    - Brochures, 1948-1960 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Silver Jubilee brochure, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 39)